Bartram, Edwin Bunting. Papers of Edwin Bunting Bartram, 1925-1963: A Guide
Papers of Edwin Bunting Bartram, 1925-1963
Botany Libraries
The collection was given to the Farlow Herbarium begining in August 1964 by Bartram himself.
Biography:
Edwin Buntin Bartram was born on July 28, 1878 in Philadelphia, PA. He dropped out of high school to support his mother and began working at the Insulated Wire Co. of Philadelphia as an office boy. He rose to the position of company manager before retiring at the age of 39.
Bartram was an outdoorsman. He loved fishing, tennis, gardening, botany, and especially bryology. He made many botanical trips with Merritt Lyndon Fernald and between 1909 and 1922 he published numerous papers on the flowering plants of Massachusetts, New Jersey, Pennsylvania, and Arizona. His first publication on bryology appeared in 1922 and never turned back. He was a member of the Academy of Natural Science,; Philadelphia Botanical Club,; Torrey Botanical Club,; New England Botanical Club, and the Sullivant Moss Society. In total Bartram contributed 143 works to bryology, including a number of books. He described many dozens of new species, and was a kind and patient tutor to the young bryologists that sought him out.
Unfortunately in the 1950's Bartram's eyesight began to fail. He began to severely limit his research to a few hours a day. In 1964 he was forced to give up on his work all together because his eyes were almost useless. On December 2, 1964 Edwin Bunting Bartram, a botanist for 55 years and a renowned bryologist for 42, died at his home in Bushkill, Pennsylvania.
References:
Barnhart, J. Botanical Notes Upon Botanists. v.1: 132. Crum, H. "A Tribute to Edwin Bunting Bartram" Bryologist 69: 125-134 (1966)
Scope Content:
Collection consist of correspondence, specimen lists, keys, and manuscripts. They deal with Bartram's bryological research both in the United States and overseas.
Series Description:
The collection is broken down into five series.
Series I - Correspondence. The correspondence dates from 1920- 1964. There are 30 boxes of correspondence. These are arranged by date, and then alphabetically within a specific date range. There are also 10 folders of miscellaneous correspondence to Bartram. These are arranged alphabetically by author and range from 1939-1967.
Series II - Specimen Lists. These are lists of mosses from various expeditions and trips. They are arranged alphabetically by location. Included are Ecuador, Samoa, New Guinea, Venezuela, Polynesia, Chile, and New Zealand. If notes or correspondence accompanied the list it will be noted in the finding aid and filed in behind the specimen list.
Series III - Keys. These are plant keys to different types of moss in different areas that Bartram traveled to. Included are New Guinea and Fiji.
Series IV - Manuscripts
Series V - Miscellaneous Materials
Container List:
- Correspondence, Series I:
  - July 1920-July 1925, Box 1 - 2
  - July 1925-March 1929, Box 3 - 5
  - February 1929-September 1932, Box 6 - 8
  - October 1932-March 1936, Box 9 - 11
  - March 1936-July 1940, Box 12 - 14
  - July 1940-May 1943, Box 15 - 16
  - May 1943-March 1947, Box 17 - 18
  - July 1947-July 1949, Box 19 - 20
  - September 1949-November 1951, Box 21 - 22
  - November 1951-May 1955, Box 23 - 24
  - June 1955-December 1958, Box 25 - 26
  - December 1958-April 1963, Box 27 - 28
  - April 1963-November 1964, Box 29 - 30
  - Carton 1
    - Correspondence to E.B. Bartram, A-B, Folder 1:
      - Andrews, A LeRoy, May 14, 1945., 1.
      - Bartlett, H.H., University of Michigan, November 15, 1944 (with attached letter from Lieutenant R.A. Copeland, November 13, 1944), 2.
      - British Museum of Natural History, June 25, 1962., 3.
      - Bunting, Charles M., December 28, 1967., 4.
    - Correspondence to E.B. Bartram from H.M. Dixon, March 8, 1935-May 2, 1936. (8 letters and 1 no date fragment), Folder 2:
    - Correspondence to E.B. Bartram, F-G, Folder 3:
      - Funch, Edye, Co. Agents, February 13, 1951, 1.
      - Funch, Edye, Co. Agents, February 20, 1951, 2.
      - Grubb, R.J., May 25, 1963, 3.
      - Grubb, R.J., July 10, 1963, 4.
    - Correspondence to E.B. Bartram, H, Folder 4:
      - Harwing, M (?), January 14, 1945, 1.
      - Herbarium en Museum Buitenzorg (M.A. Donk), May 10, 1949, 2.
      - Herbarium en Museum Buitenzorg (M.A. Donk), November 18, 1949, 3.
    - Correspondence to E.B. Bartram, J.P. Reiss Co., February 19, 1951 - March 21, 1951. (5 letters), Folder 5:
    - Correspondence to E.B. Bartram, Kemeenterian Pertanian, Herbarium Bogoriense, December 16, 1950 - April 6, 1957. (4 letters), Folder 6:
    - Correspondence to E.B. Bartram, M-N, Folder 7:
      - MacFadden, Fay A., November 23, 1943, 1.
      - Merrill, E.D. (Arnold Arboretum), January 29, 1941, 2.
      - Museum o'Histoire Naturelle; (Pierre Allogore), November 10, 1944, 3.
      - New York Botanical Garden; (Fred Seaver), October 27, 1943 5. New York Botanical Garden (H.W. Rickett), August 22, 1943, 4.
    - Correspondence to E.B. Bartram, P-S, Folder 8:
      - Oklahoma Agricultural and Mechanical College; (Gilford Ikenberry), May 1, 1942, 1.
      - Phillips, Mrs. L.H., March 6, 1939, 2.
      - Spiers, Mrs. Alexander Guy Holborn, July 20, 1946, 3.
    - Correspondence to E.B. Bartram, Ruth Svihla, January 7, 1953 - June 1, 1954. (3 letters and misc. plant lists and notes, undated), Folder 9:
    - Correspondence to E.B. Bartram, T-V, Folder 10:
      - Trotter, Leslie B.C., December 11, 1947, 1.
      - Verdoorn, Frans (Chronica Botanica), May 16, 1946, 2.
      - Verdoorn, Frans; (Chronica Botanica), June 7, 1946, 3.
      - Verdoorn, Frans (Chronica Botanica), June 13, 1946, 4.
      - Verdoorn, Frans (Chronica Botanica), August 24, 1946, 5.
      - Verdoorn, Frans (Chronica Botanica), November 26, 1946, 6.
- Specimen Lists, Series II:
  - Carton 1
    - List of mosses from Chile, sent to Bartram from E. Barros. Letter from Barro also included, 1950., Folder 11:
    - Mosses of the Cambridge Expedition to the Cordillera Oriental, 1957., Folder 12:
    - Two lists - Mosses from Ecuador, 1951 and Ecuador mosses collected by L.R. Holdridge., Folder 13:
    - List of Borneo mosses from Manilla, Folder 14:
    - List of mosses from New Guinea, sent to Bartram from R.D. Hoogland along with accompanying correspondence, 1962. Also Brass and Papua, New Guinea moss list and correspondence, 1940., Folder 15:
    - List of mosses from New Zealand by Berggren., Folder 16:
    - List of mosses from Panama, Folder 17:
    - List of mosses from Polynesia and list of mosses loaned to E.B. Bartram from Bernise P. Bishop Museum, Hawaii, 1935., Folder 18:
    - List of mosses from Samoa collected by T.G. Yunker and Samoan mosses of Upolu., Folder 19:
    - Of Venezuelan mosses collected by Maguire,; Wurdack, and Steyermark, Folder 20:
    - Unlabeled plant lists, Folder 21:
    - Specimen Labels, Folder 22:
- Keys, Series III:
  - Carton 1
    - Keys to the genera of ephemeraceae, Folder 23:
    - Keys to the genera of pottiaceae, Folder 24:
    - New Guinea keys, Folder 25- Folder 26:
    - Fiji notes and keys, Folder 27- Folder 29:
- Manuscripts, Series IV:
  - Carton 1
    - Africa, Folder 30:; - "Contribution to the mosses of Gough Island", Revue Bryologique et Lichenologique 28, 1959.; - "Plants collected by the Vernay Nyasaland Expedition of 1946", Memoirs of the New York Botanical Garden. 8 (3): 191-197.
    - British West Indies, Folder 31:; - "Moses of St. Vincent British West Indies", Revue Bryologique et Lichenologique 25. 1956.; - "Moses of Dominica, British West Indies", Bulletin of the British Museum (natural history) Botany. 2 (2), 1955.
    - Burma, Folder 32:; - "Burma Mosses", Farlowiana 1(2), July 1943. "Burma Mosses II", Revue Bryologique et Lichenologique, 23, 1954.
    - Canada, Folder 33:; - "Mosses of the Ungava Peninsula, northeastern Canada", The Bryologist 57: 273-278, 1954.
    - Chile Argentina, Folder 34:; - "Mosses of Chile and Argentina, mainly collected by R. Santesson", Svensk botanisk tidskrift utgifven af svenska botaniska foreningen. 46, 1952.
    - Costa Rica, Folder 35:; - "Additional Costa Rican Mosses IV", (published?)
    - Cuba, Folder 36:; - "Pseudohypnella in Cuba, a new genus to North America", (published?)
    - Ecuador, Folder 37:; - "Mosses of the Ecuadorian Andies" collected by P.R. Bill. Bulletin of the British Museum (natural history) Botany, 2(2), 1955.; - "Mosses of Cerro Antisana, Ecuadorian Andes”, Revue Bryologique et Lichenologique, 33, 1965.
    - Fiji, Folder 38:; - "Additions to the Mosses of Fiji", The Brycologist 47, 1944.; - "Additional Fijian Mosses", Occasional Papers, Bernice P. Bishop Museum, 19, 1948 (and manuscript proof); - "Additional Fijian Mosses II", Occasional Papers, Bernice P. Bishop Museum, 20, 1950; - "Additional Fijian Mosses", Journal of the Washington Academy of Science. 46, 1956.
    - Fiji, Folder 39:; - "Contribution to the Mosses of Fiji", Occasional Papers, Bernice P. Bishop Museum, 1936.
    - Guam, Folder 40:; - "Mosses of Guam, Mariana Islands", The Brycologist, 63, 1960.
    - Guatemala, Folder 41:; - "New Species New Combinations of Guatemalan Moses II", The Brycologist, 50, 1947.
    - Himalayas, Folder 42:; - "Northwest Himalayan Mosses", Bulletin of the Torrey Botanical Club, 82, 1955.; - "Northwestern Himalayan Mosses, II", Revue Bryologique et Lichenologique, 29, 1960.
    - New Guinea, Folder 43:; - "Additions to the Moss Flora of the Netherlands New Guinea", Svensk botanisk tidskrift utgifven af svenska botaniska foreningen, 54, 1960.; - "Mosses of the Western Highlands of Eastern New Guinea", Revue Bryologique et Lichenologique, 30, 1961.
    - New Guinea, Folder 44:; - "Additional Mosses from Northeast New Guinea", Svensk botanisk tidskrift utgifven af svenska botaniska foreningen, 47, 1953.; - "Mosses of the Moroke District, Northeast New Guinea", The Brycologist, 48, 1944.
    - New Guinea, Folder 45:; - "Mosses of Eastern Papau, New Guinea", Brittonia, 9, 1957. Also includes corresponding notes and letters. - "Mosses of Papau, New Guinea", Farlowia, 1(1), January 1943
    - New Guinea, Folder 46:; - "Mosses of D'Entrecasteaux Group Louisade Archipelago, Papau, New Guinea", Blumea X (1), 1960. Two copies of this article.
    - New Guinea, Folder 47:; - "Contributions to the Mosses of the Highlands of Eastern New Guinea", (published?). Two copies of this article.
    - Mexico, Folder 48:; - "Alpine Mosses from Mexico", Revue Bryologique et Lichenologique 15, 1945.; - "Calcareous Mosses from the Sierra Madre Oriental, Mexico", Notulae Naturae of the Academy of Natural Sciences, 229, 1951.
    - Mexico, Folder 49:; - "Mosses from Western Coahuila", Revue Bryologique et Lichenologique 18, 1949.; - "Contributions to the Moss Flora of Southeastern Mexico", The Bryologist, 50, 1947.; - "Mosses of Northern New Mexico collected by Brother Arsene". Annales de Cryptogamie Exotique, 4, 1931.
    - Okinawa, Folder 50:; - "Okinawa Mosses", The Bryologist, 50, 1947.
    - Philippines, Folder 51:; - "New and Noteworthy Philippine Mosses", Farlowia, 1(4), 1944.; - "Mosses of Philippines", Index and Corrections.
    - Polynesia, Folder 52:; - "Mosses of Southeastern Polynesia". (published?) Two copies of this article.
    - Samoa, Folder 53:; - "Mosses of the Manua Group, Samoa". (published?); - "Mosses of Upola, Western Samoa", Occasional Papers, Bernice P. Bishop Museum, 22 (3), 1957
    - Tierra del Fuego, Folder 54:; - " New Mosses from Tierra del Fuego". Farlowia, 2(3).
    - Tropical America, Folder 55:; - "Mosses as Indicators of Plant Distribution in Tropical America".
    - United States - Alaska, Folder 56:; - "Mosses of the Neultin Lake Expedition, Keewatin, Notulae Naturae of the Academy of Natural Sciences, 1947",; - "Mosses of the Aleutin Islands, Alaska", Botaniska Notiser, 1938; - "Mosses from the United States Antarctic Services Expedition", The Bryologist, 60, 1957. Proof is also included.
    - United States - Southwest, Folder 57:; - "A New Weisia and a New Tortula from the Southwestern United States", The Bryologist, 48, 1945.
    - United States - Texas, Folder 58:; - "Mosses of Trans-Pecos", 1940. Two copies of this article.
    - United States - Hawaii, Folder 59:; - "Mosses Collected by Hawaiian Bog Survey of 1938", Occasional Papers, Bernice P. Bishop Museum, 16 (14), April 1942.; - "Pacific Outpost Mosses", The Bryologist, 47, 1944.
    - United States - Hawaii, Folder 60:; - "Supplement to the Manual of Hawaiian Mosses", Occasional Papers, Bernice P. Bishop Museum, 15 (8), July 1939. Two copies and corresponding notes.
    - United States - Hawaii, Folder 61:; - "Manual of Hawaiian Mosses", Bulletin, Bernice P. Bishop Museum, 101, 1933. Part I
    - United States - Hawaii, Folder 62:; - "Manual of Hawaiian Mosses", Bulletin, Bernice P. Bishop Museum, 101, 1933. Part II
    - United States - Venezuala, Folder 63:; - "Mosses of the New York Botanical Garden Venezuelan Expedition, 1950-1951". (published?); - "Supplement to the Kunhardt Venezuelan Expedition, 1948-1949, Territorio Amazones Brazil". (published?); - "Venezuelan Mosses Collected by Julian A. Steyermark", Boletin de la Sociedad Venezolana de Ciencias Naturales, 25, 1963.
    - United States, Folder 64:; - Unidentified Manuscripts
    - United States, Folder 65:; - Unidentified Galley Proofs
- Miscellaneous Materials, Series V:
  - Blank postcard of Bartram mansion, Philadelphia, PA., Folder 66:
  - "La vegitation muscinale des antilles francaises et son interet dans la valorisation sylvicole" by H. Stehle, 1943. Inscribed to E.B. Bartram, June 16, 1944., Folder 67:
  - Book review by Bartram for Liverworts of Southern Michigan by William Campbell Smith., Folder 68:
  - Christmas Card from Chronica Botanica, 1946., Folder 69:
  - Committee for Nomenclature of Bryophytes Circular, February 1955., Folder 70:
  - Order forms for Revised International Rules of Botanical Nomenclature., Folder 71:
  - Chronica Botanica flyers (2)., Folder 72:
  - New Guinea card file of specimen names, Folder 73: